Guide to the Mary Moline Research Collection on Albert Gallatin MC 189
New York University Archives
Mary Moline Research Collection on Albert Gallatin
1991-2005
1928-2005
New York University Archives
Moline, Mary
MC 189
1.75 Linear Feet in 1 record carton and 1 custom box
Mary Moline is the author of many books, including America's Vindicated Statesman: Albert Gallatin. This collection is her research on Albert Gallatin in the form of books, secondary material printouts, and copies of Gallatin's letters.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials found in collection; there is no documentation concerning the provenance of these materials. The accession number associated with this collection is 05.017.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged by subject in three series:
I. Research Files on Albert Gallatin
II. Books on Albert Gallatin
III. Memorabilia
Missing Title
Series I: Research Files on Albert Gallatin
Subseries I: Research for America's Vindicated Statesman Part 1
Subseries II: Research for America's Vindicated Statesman Part 2
Series II: Books on Albert Gallatin
Biographical Note
Mary Moline has written books on many topics, including an anthology on Henry Ford (Best of Ford: A Collection of Short Stories and Essays); works on Norman Rockwell (The Norman Rockwell Collectibles Value Guide: The Little Rockwell Book); and a Christmas story entitled "Mimi." She is also a motivational speaker and the founder of the International White Cross, an organization of disaster victims helping other disaster victims.
Albert Gallatin was born in Geneva, Switzerland in 1761. As a youth, he immigrated to the United States, where he quickly became involved in American politics. As a House of Representatives member he was the leader of the Democratic-Republican Party and served as Secretary of the Treasury from 1801 to 1813. Following his career as a politician and diplomat, Gallatin helped found New York University in 1831. The Gallatin School of Individualized Study is named in honor of his contributions to the University.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of files relating to Mary Moline's research on Albert Gallatin for her book America's Vindicated Statesman: Albert Gallatin. Secondary material about Gallatin's life and work may be found in this collection, as well as photocopies of his writings and correspondence. Photocopies of were created in 2004. The collection also contains books written about Gallatin and a Christmas ornament depicting United States Coast Guard vessel, the USCG Gallatin. Handouts and pamphlets from different places, such as Gallatin's home at Friendship Hill, are also among the research materials.
Memorabilia.; Moline, Mary; Gallatin, Albert, 1761-1849
- Series I: Research Files on Albert Gallatin
  Scope and Contents
  Series I includes files related to Albert Gallatin that were printed out from the internet.
  - Subseries I: Research for America's Vindicated Statesman Part 1
    Subseries I includes research for America's Vindicated Statesman that was printed out from the internet.
    - Biographical Information on Albert Gallatin, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Copies of Gallatin's Writings, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Copies of Writings to and from Gallatin, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Copies of Gallatin's Writings on Oregon, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Friendship Hill-Home of Albert Gallatin- booklet and postcard, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - The National Road: Main Street of America- booklet, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - TIME Special Edition: The Making of America, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Subseries II: Research for America's Vindicated Statesman Part 2
    Subseries II includes research for America's Vindicated Statesman that was printed out from the internet.
    - Biographical Information and Notes, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Handouts and Booklets on Gallatin, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Research on Friendship Hill, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Gallatin Stamps, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Research on Gallatin's Legacy (1of 2), 2004 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Research on Gallatin's Legacy (2 of 2), 2004
    - Library of Congress References, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Final Cover Art CD-R, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - US Coast Guard Gallatin Ornament, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Series II: Books on Albert Gallatin
  Series II includes published books related to Albert Gallatin.
  - The Correspondence of John Badollet and Albert Gallatin 1804-1836 edited by Gayle Thornbrough, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Albert Gallatin: Jeffersonian Financier and Diplomat by Raymond Walters Jr., 1957 (Box 1)
  - Albert Gallatin's Vision of Democratic Stability by L.B. Kuppenheimer, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Albert Gallatin and the Oregon Problem by Frederick Merk, 1950 (Box 1)
  - Albert Gallatin by John Austen Stevens, 1898 (Box 1)
  - The Diary of James Gallatin edited by Count Gallatin, 1930 (Box 1)
  - American Woodland Indians by Michael Johnson, 1992 (Box 1)
- Memorabilia, 1991
  Series III includes memorabilia related to Albert Gallatin.
  - Christmas ornament depicting United States Coast Guard vessel, the USCG Gallatin, 1991 (Box 2)
    ID Number: 514. Description: Christmas ornament showing USCG Gallatin. Creator/Donor/Subject: Mary Moline Research Collection.